-早安，斯达顿太太 -早安
- Good morning, Mrs. Statons. - Morning, madam.
你迟到了！
Late! Late!
终于来了
At last.
很抱歉，我们迟到了
Sorry we're late.
放在后面吧
Go in the back.
妈的！妈的！
Oh, fuck! Fuck!
妈的！
Fuck!
Oh, fuck!
妈的！开你的车子吧
Fuck! Right, we take yours.
它的时速只有四十哩
It only goes 40 miles an hour.
那个出口？
What turnoff?
千万不要是B359
Better not be the B359.
是B359
It's the B359.
去他的！
Fuck it!
该死！
Fuck!
见鬼
Fuck.
来吧
Come on.
妈的！
Fuck!
妈的
Fuck.
该死！
Fuck!
见鬼
Fuck.
见他妈的鬼
糟了
Bugger.
你好漂亮
Look at you in white.
有没有打结了呢？
Is it twisted?
你好！你很漂亮
Hello! You look lovely.
你好，查尔斯！
Hello, Charles!
你这次迟到得最不同凡响
There's a greatness to your lateness.
我已拼尽全力
It's not achieved without real suffering.
非常抱歉
I am so, so sorry.
婚礼后我会自杀 若这样会让你好过点的话
I'll kill myself after the service, if that's any consolation.
没关系，有汤姆作后备
Doesn't matter. Tom was standing by.
谢了，你真是圣人
Thanks, Tom. You're a saint.
而且发型还棒透了
And a disastrous haircut.
你记得带戒指吧？
You haven't forgotten the rings?
记得
No.
最讨厌别人迟到
Hate people being late.
开始了
Here we go.
她很美丽吧？
Oh, isn't she lovely?
你一定是瞎了眼 她像一大团棉花糖
Scarlett, you're blind. She looks like a big meringue.
亲爱的朋友 欢迎在安格斯和…
Dear friends, what a joy it is to welcome you to our church...
萝拉的大日子 莅临本教堂
...on this wonderful day for Angus and Laura.
在仪式开始之前，请大家一起…
Before we start the service, let us all join together...
颂唱第一首圣歌
...in the first hymn.
远古时代的…
人们的足迹
印在英国青葱的山岭
而圣洁的…
子民
在英国翠绿的草原上…
显现过
那副神圣的面容
曾照耀在…
阴霾密布的山丘上
耶路撒冷…
在邪恶的试炼里
兴建起来
思嘉
Scarlett.
亲爱的各位，我们聚集在这里
Dearly beloved, we are gathered here...
在上帝和会众的面前
...in the sight of God and in the face of this congregation...
跟这两位共订鸳盟的男女一起
...to join together this man and this woman in holy matrimony.
这个光荣的人生阶段
Which is an honorable estate...
由混沌初开之际已经制定
...instituted in the time of man's innocency.
-我很快回来 -若有人能够提出…
- Back in a sec. - lf any man can show...
这两人不能结为合法夫妇的…
...any just cause or impediment...
理由或障碍
...why they may not be lawfully joined together...
马上提出来，否则请保持缄默
...let him speak now or forever hold his peace.
你愿意承诺去爱她
Do you promise to love her...
安慰她，以她为荣 无论疾病健康
...comfort her, honor and keep her in sickness and in health...
都从一而终
...and forsaking all others...
在有生之年都视她为妻子吗？
...keep thee only unto her for as long as ye both shall live?
我愿意
I do.
疼爱和珍视他
To love and to cherish...
至死不渝
Till death us do part.
...till death us do part.
我再次向你许下承诺
Thereto, I pledge thee my troth.
And thereto, I pledge thee my troth.
你有戒指吗？
Do you have the ring?
我替你戴上戒指，娶你为妻
With this ring, I thee wed.
我以谦卑的躯体崇敬你
With my body, I thee worship.
我把世上最好的东西奉献给你
And with all my worldly goods, I do thee endow.
And with all my worldly goods, I thee endow.
若我单凭人和天使的口才说话 当中却没有爱的话
If I speak with the tongues of men and of angels, but have not love...
我就是吵耳的铙钹
...I am become a sounding brass or a clanging cymbal.
说得好
Good point.
没有你，我不能微笑
我无法欢笑歌咏
一事无成
你悲伤时，我也感到难过
我感到难过
你快乐所以我快乐
若你知道我的经历
帽子很漂亮
Great hat.
谢了，我特地买的
Thanks. I bought it specially.
这样好了
There.
各就各位
Get in position, please.
谢谢，笑一个
Thank you. Smile.
场面很大，你意下如何？
Splendid, I thought. What did you think?
I thought, splendid. What did you think?
场面很大
Splendid, I thought.
思嘉，好美的洋装！
Scarlett, fabulous dress!
教会的紫色配上异教的橘色
Ecclesiastical purple and pagan orange...
象征着异教和基督教在婚姻里
...symbolizing the magical symbiosis in marriage...
奇妙的共生的现象？
...between heathen and Christian traditions?
对
That's right.
漂亮，再拍一个
Lovely. And again.
知道戴着黑帽的女孩是谁吗？
Any idea who the girl in the black hat is?
她叫嘉莉
Name's Carrie.
蛮漂亮的
She's pretty.
美国人
American.
真有趣
Interesting.
是荡妇
Slut.
真的吗？
Really?
从前替时尚杂志工作 现居美国
Used to work at Vogue. Lives in America now.
只会跟魅力非凡的人交往
Only goes out with very glamorous people.
没你的份
Quite out of your league.
那我就放心了，谢了
Well, that's a relief. Thanks.
待会见
See you there.
进去吧
Off you go.
对，宴会上见
Right. Reception.
再见！…
Bye! Bye!
还有人踩到牛屎吗？
Anyone else tread in a cowpat?
我想没有了，待会见
No, thought not. See you in a mo.
若他不是我哥哥 我还会这么讨厌他吗？
Do you think I'd hate him as much if he wasn't my brother?
真不想一身臭味出席酒会 而失去碰到姻缘的机会
Don't want to blow chances for romance... ...by smelling of dung at the reception.
我从不懂怎么应付 这种场面
Oh, God. I never know what to say in these wretched lineups.
很简单，热情地拥抱他 说新娘好像怀孕了
It's a cinch. Give a big, warm hug and say the bride looks pregnant.
或是按惯例说：『你很自豪吧』
Or stick with tradition, "You must be very proud."
愿主保佑我们
Heaven preserve us.
你很自豪吧
You must be very proud.
谢谢
Indeed.
你好
Hello.
-你好 -你好
- Hello. - Hello.
-我们见过面的，我是理查 -对
- Hi, we've met. It's Richard Maples. - Oh, yes.
王八蛋
Bastard.
-好吗，伯纳 -好吗，查理
- Hello, Bern. - Hello, Chuck.
两杯，谢谢
Two, please.
-好好享受 -保重了
- You have fun, now. - Take care.
你好
Oh, hello.
Hi.
-要喝一杯吗？ -谢谢
- You want one of these? - Oh, thank you.
-我… -好吗，查尔斯
- l... - Hello, Charles.
约翰，你好吗？
Hello, dear John. How are you?
我很好，这位是…
Good. This is...
嘉莉
- Carrie. - Carrie.
-很高兴认识你，我叫约翰 -你好
- Delighted. I'm John. - Hi, John.
你的女朋友好吗？
How's your girlfriend?
她不再是我的女朋友了
She's no longer my girlfriend.
别难过 人们说她一直跟陶比有染
Don't be too gloomy. Rumor is she never stopped bonking Toby de Lisle.
她是我的妻子
She's now my wife.
太好了…恭喜你
Excellent. Excellent. Congratulations.
我失陪了
Excuse me.
有孩子了没？
Any kids or anything, John?
打算何时生…
Do we hear the patter of tiny...
一个？
...feet?
没有
No.
来日方长，对吗？不忙的
Well, there's plenty of time for that, isn't there? No hurry.
你好吗？
Hi. How are you?
我叫菲欧娜
My name's Fiona.
我叫吉罗德
I'm Gerald.
你做哪一行业？
What do you do?
我在受训，预备当神父
I'm training to be a priest.
我的天！
Good Lord!
你会主持结婚典礼吗？
Do you do weddings?
现在还不能，将来一定会
No. No, not yet. I will, though, of course.
简直是精神折磨
Jolly nerve-racking.
就像初夜一样
Yes, rather like the first time one has sex.
我想是吧
Well, I suppose so.
当然没那么混乱 也不会用那么多保险套
Rather less messy, of course. And far less call for condoms.
你觉得怎么样？
记得那次你把爸爸的船开动
螺旋桨把我的腿打碎吗？
这次更烂
那个穿灰衣服的男孩是谁？
Who's that boy over there in the gray?
他叫大卫
His name's David.
很有魅力，是不是？
Something of a dish, isn't he?
我一向都是这样想的
Well, I've always thought so.
他们干嘛…？
Why are they...?
-魅力小子是聋子 -可惜
- The dish can't hear. - Oh!
天啊
Gosh.
对，不能说话…
Yeah, silent...
但却引人入胜
...but deadly attractive.
就是这样
Bang, bang, bang. That's it.
请到帐篷就坐，晚餐准备好了
Into the marquee, please. Dinner is served.
你好吗？
How do you do?
我叫汤姆，很高兴认识你
Hello, Tom. Splendid to meet you.
令人兴奋
Very exciting.
你好
Hi.
我叫思嘉
My name's Scarlett.
别让我喝太多 否则我会很轻佻的
Don't let me drink too much, because I'll get really flirty.
你好吗？我叫查尔斯
How do you do? My name is Charles.
别说笑，查尔斯已经死了二十年
Don't be ridiculous. Charles died 20 years ago.
他是另一个查尔斯吧
Must be a different Charles.
你说我不认得自己的兄弟吗？
You're saying I don't know my own brother?
不是的
No, no.
各位，很抱歉打扰你们吃甜点
Ladies and gentlemen, sorry to drag you from your desserts.
身为伴郎我觉得 我要说几句话
There are one or two little things I feel I should say as best man.
我只是第二次当伴郎
This is only the second time I've ever been best man.
希望我还算称职吧
I hope I did the job okay that time.
至少上一对夫妇 还愿意跟我说话
The couple in question are at least still talking to me.
很可惜，他们却互不理睬
Unfortunately, they're not actually talking to each other.
他们几个月前离婚了
The divorce came through a couple of months ago.
但他们向我保证此事跟我无关
But I'm assured it had absolutely nothing to do with me.
宝拉显然在我演讲之前
Apparently, Paula knew Pierce slept with her sister...
已知道皮尔斯跟她的妹妹睡
...before I mentioned it in the speech.
可是他跟岳母睡却真是意外
The fact that he slept with her mother came as a surprise...
但我却以为 这段两日婚姻是…
...but I think was incidental to the nightmare of recrimination...
随之而来的 互相责备和暴力所导致的
...and violence that became their two-day marriage.
说够了，我要说的是安格斯
Anyway, enough of that. My job today is to talk about Angus.
他并没有秘密
And there are no skeletons in his cupboard...
我是这样想的
...or so I thought.
我待会会去求证，我想说的是…
I'll get to that in a minute. I'd just like to say this:
一如以往…
I am as ever...
对于像安格斯和萝拉一样 愿意许下承诺的人
...in bewildered awe of anyone who makes this kind of commitment...
我都异常敬佩
...that Angus and Laura have made today.
我自知办不到
I know I couldn't do it...
他们办得到，实在太好了
...and I think it's wonderful they can.
说回安格斯和他的同类
So back to Angus and those sheep.
各位先生、女士，请举杯
So, ladies and gentlemen, if you'd raise your glasses.
-敬一对壁人 -好！
- The adorable couple. - Yes!
敬一对壁人
The adorable couple!
替我吻新娘！
Get one for me, Angus!
我第一次看见盖瑞夫跳舞时
The first time I saw Gareth on the dance floor...
还以为会弄出人命
...I feared lives would be lost.
她很漂亮
She's a pretty girl.
你目不转睛地看着她 一见钟情吗？
The one you can't take your eyes off. Love at first sight?
不，我曾跟她的舞伴玩橄榄球
No, it's the bloke she's dancing with. I played rugby with him at school.
我在想他是打哪个位置的
I'm trying to remember what position he played.
我们来辩论一下
Though, let's say for the sake of argument...
人们参加婚礼时会爱上别人
...one did take a fancy to someone at a wedding.
有没有人可以就这样说
Do you think there are people who can just say:
『宝贝，我叫查尔斯 你今晚走运了？』
"Hi, babe. My name's Charles. This is your lucky night"?
他们肯定不是英国人
If there are, they're not English.
的确如此
Quite.
三个星期是最低限度的试探期
Three weeks is about my question-popping minimum.
你知道我爱你的，是不是？
You know I love you, Jean, don't you?
我爱你…
I love you. I love you.
麦克，虽然我不认识你
And Mike, I've never met you before...
但我真的很爱你
...but I love you very much. I really do.
别理会她，她喝醉了
Ignore her, she's drunk.
至少我希望她是
At least I hope she is.
否则我的麻烦可大了
Otherwise, I'm in real trouble.
你过得怎么样？
How's it going, Lyds?
烂透了
Bloody awful.
亲爱的，怎么了？
Oh, dear. What's the problem?
大家都说我会有艳遇
I was promised sex. Everybody said it:
你是伴娘，会有艳遇 推也推不掉
"You'll be a bridesmaid, you'll get sex. You'll be fighting them off."
可是现在简直是门可罗雀
But not so much as a tongue in sight.
我的意思是，若你想要…
Well, I mean, if you fancy...
干什么
...anything...
我永远都会…
...I could always...
别说无聊事了
Oh, don't be ridiculous, Bernard.
-我才不是那么绝望呢 -当然了
- I'm not that desperate. - No, right. Of course.
有道理
Fair enough.
说得好
It's a good point.
再见！
Bye!
好好享受良辰美景！
Have a lovely, lovely time!
再见！
Bye!
你今晚住在哪？
Where are you staying tonight, Charles?
思嘉和我在旅舍里下榻
Scarlett and I are at some pub.
好像叫什么幸运船的 不是所有人都住那里吗？
The Lucky Boat, something like that. Aren't we all?
不，计划有些微变动
No. Slight change of plan.
他们要到我家去
The others are coming back to my place.
南茜会在我们玩拼字游戏时 弄宵夜给我们吃
Nansy's there. Might cook us eggs and bac over a late-night Scrabble.
不知道你有没有兴趣参加
Wondered if you'd like to join.
好极了，非常谢谢你
Yeah, great. Thanks very much.
有房间给思嘉睡吗？
Is there room for Scarlett?
当然有，一共137间房
Oh, absolutely. 137 rooms, actually.
你是全英国最富有的人吗？
Tommy, are you the richest man in England?
不是！
No, no!
我们大概是第七位吧
I believe we're about seventh.
最富有的当然是女王
The queen, obviously.
那个布兰森也混得很不错
And that Branson bloke's doing terribly well.
真是好消息
Well, excellent news.
我去告诉思嘉
I'll go tell Scarlett.
好的
Yeah.
除非…
That's...
你走桃花运
...unless you get lucky first.
算了吧！快走…
Forget about it! Get out of it! Get out. Go on!
你好
Hi.
你好，还以为你已经走了
Hi. Hi! I thought you'd gone.
我还在，我想知道你今晚 住在哪
Not yet. I was just wondering where you were staying tonight.
这个…
Well...
我本来是住在一间叫什么…
I was staying at some pub called The Lucky...
-幸运船的旅馆里 -是船夫
...Boat or something like that. - Boatman.
对
Right.
不过我现在要跟朋友 到朋友的家里
But now I'm going to stay at some friend's house with some friends.
正确来说，那是一座大城堡
Well, I think enormous castle is a more accurate description.
真可惜，我也是住在船夫旅馆
That's too bad because I'm at The Boatman.
我很高兴
Well, it was nice...
虽然还不算认识你
...not quite meeting you.
那篇演讲词很精彩
It was a great speech.
谢了
Thanks.
我要走了
Well, I'm going now.
不！不…别走
No! No, no, don't go.
我们可以聊聊，现在还早呢
We can meet now. The evening's just getting going.
你我都知道那只是自欺欺人
We both know that's a big lie.
该死
Fuck.
城堡在召唤了，你清醒吗？
The castle beckons, I think, Tom. Are you sober?
绝对清醒，我整晚都喝橘子汁
Absolutely. Orange juice all night.
来吧
Come on.
各位再见了！
Bye, everybody!
伯纳！
Bernard!
支持你的男人
哔…
向全世界说你爱他
给予他无尽的爱
支持--
汤姆，可以停车吗？
Tom, can you stop the car?
停车！
Stop the car!
对不起，我还是想…
Sorry. Sorry. I just think I might...
留在旅馆里
...stay in that pub after all.
干嘛？
Why on earth?
我在研究名字中有船字的旅馆
No, seriously. I'm researching pubs with "boat" in the title.
希望能有决定性的成果
I hope to produce the definitive work.
-请便 -实在荒谬
- Please yourself. - It's a silly thing, you know?
对
Right.
古怪的决定
Odd decision.
你好
Hello.
Hi.
你好
结果房间不够分配
Turned out there wasn't room for all of us.
你说那是一座城堡
You said it was a castle.
的确是城堡
No, it is a castle.
是很小的城堡
It's just a very, very small one.
只不过楼上楼下各一间房 真罕见
Tiny. Just one up, one down, which is rare.
要喝点什么吗？
Drink, sir?
我想喝威士忌，谢谢
Yeah. I'd like a glass of whiskey, please. Thanks.
-你要喝吗？ -听来不错
- Do you want? - Yeah, sounds good.
-给这位女士多调一杯 -要两杯吗？
- Make another one for the lady. - Doubles, sir?
谢了
Thanks.
原来你也在这里，你好吗？
You here too? How are you?
你好，我很好
Hello. I'm fine.
-有没有见过嘉莉？ -谁？
- Haven't seen Carrie, have you? - Who?
嘉莉，来自美国的美腿女郎
Carrie. American girl. Lovely legs.
是婚礼上的宾客，芳香扑鼻
Wedding guest. Nice smell.
抱歉，没看见
No. Sorry.
该死！可恶
Damn. Blast.
还以为已经得手了
I think I was in there.
若你看见她 可以告诉她我回房了吗？
If you see her, could you tell her I've gone to my room?
好的
Yeah, yeah.
-威士忌 -谢谢
- Your whiskey, sir. - Thank you.
这杯是…
And one for the...
上路用的，好极
Road. Lovely.
我想要喝一杯，一起喝好吗？
I think I might have one. Mind if I join you?
好的，太好了
No. It'd be lovely.
一杯威士忌，一支雪茄
Another glass of whiskey and a cigar.
等等，要一瓶吧
Hold on. Make that a bottle.
让我们静下来 看看能否喝到天亮
We might as well settle in. Let's see if we can push on till dawn.
-婚礼办得真好 -对
- Lovely wedding. - Yes, yes.
我跟他哥哥一起念书，那厮很棒
I was at school with his brother Bufty. Tremendous bloke.
他是宿舍的舍监，经常欺负我
He was head of my house. Buggered me senseless.
教我认识人生真谛
Taught me things about life.
你在哪认识他的？
Where you know him from?
大学
University.
真好…
Splendid. Splendid. Yep.
我没上大学 觉得没此必要
I didn't go myself. I couldn't see the point.
我在金融界工作 要诗歌来干嘛？
When you're working the money markets... ...what use is Wordsworth gonna be?
打扰了 你妻子问你可否马上上楼？
Excuse me. Your wife says, "Could you come upstairs at once?
若你忘了的话，是12号房
Room 12, in case you can't remember."
-我妻子？ -是的
- My wife? - Yes, sir.
是我妻子！…
Oh, my wife! My wife!
你醉了，连妻子也忘记了
You are drunk. You can't remember you got a wife.
对
Yeah, yeah.
-若你不介意的话… -不介意，你走吧
- Do you mind if I...? - No, no. Off you go.
-祝你好运 -谢了
- Best of luck. - Thanks.
幸好我还是独身 可以继续寻找凯蒂的芳踪
Lucky bachelor me, I'll have another search for that Katie creature.
-是嘉莉 -对，漂亮的小妞
- Carrie. - That's the one. Damn fine filly.
我知道我得手了
I think I'm in there.
-你好 -你好
- Hi. - Hello.
很对不起
Sorry about that.
没关系，他很难缠的
That's fine. He was hard to get rid of.
对
Yeah.
这样…
So...
也许我们可以…
Maybe we could just...
先躲一会，然后…
...skulk around here for a bit, and then...
再下去
...go back down.
好主意 我不是经常都偷偷摸摸的
Now that's a thought. I don't usually skulk a lot...
但有需要的话，我也会躲起来
...but I suppose I could skulk if skulking were required.
你经常都是鬼鬼祟祟的吗？
Do you skulk regularly?
不，通常我不觉得…
No. No, I don't normally...
自己是个逃避者，不过…
...think of myself as a skulker, but...
你何不进来先躲一会
Well, why don't you come in and skulk for a while...
再作打算
...and we'll see.
新郎新娘没在教堂里接吻
I noticed the bride and groom didn't kiss in the church...
有点奇怪
...which is kind of strange.
在我的家乡，人们经常接吻
Where I come from, kissing is very big.
是吗？你说得对，我们较保守
Is it? Yes, well, you're right. We probably are more reserved.
『你可以跟新娘接吻了』 没列在经文中
"You may now kiss the bride," isn't in the Book of Common Prayer.
我总害怕自己会一时冲动而越轨
I always worry I'll go too far in the heat of the moment.
你觉得怎样才算是越轨呢？
How far do you think too far would be, then?
我不知道
Oh, I don't know.
也许…
Maybe...
这样还可以吧
...that would be all right.
这样很好
That would be fine.
事实上，这是有拒绝的意思
In fact, it might be a bit dismissive.
也许这样…
Maybe this...
会比较好
...would be better.
若再进一步就会有危险了
Yeah, I think it would be dangerous to take it any further.
我的意思是…
I mean...
你知道…
You know...
这样也许有点过分了？
That might be taking it a little far.
这样又如何？
What about this?
那个牧师会觉得事情失控了吗？
You think the vicar would think things had slipped a bit out of his control?
他会
I think he might.
这种事跟婚礼比起来…
This kind of thing is really better suited...
更适合度蜜月
...to the honeymoon than to the service itself.
为何要叫做蜜月呢？
Why do you think it's called a honeymoon?
不知道，可能是…
I don't know. I suppose it's...
『蜜』是因为这段时间甜如蜜
..."honey" because it's sweet as honey.
至于『月』，那是因为丈夫…
And "moon" because it was the first time...
第一次看见太太的屁股
...a husband got to see his wife's bottom.
怎么了？
What's happening?
我要走了
I have to go.
-到哪去？ -美国
- Where? - America.
真可悲
That is a tragedy.
在我离开之前
Just before I go...
你想于何时宣布订婚的事？
...when were you thinking of announcing the engagement?
对不起，谁要订婚？
Sorry. Whose engagement?
我们的
Ours.
既然我们已经睡过了，应该结婚
I assumed since we slept together, we'd be getting married.
你觉得呢？
What did you think?
什么？
What?
我…
I...
你知道
Gosh, you know, that...
这种事要仔细考虑清楚
...takes a lot of thinking about, that kind of thing.
很明显的，我…
Obviously, I'm...
你在开玩笑
You're joking.
天！还以为这是 『致命的吸引力』
God! For a moment there, I thought I was in Fatal Attraction.
你是葛伦克萝斯 我的兔宝宝则在锅子里
I thought you were Glenn Close, and I'd find my pet rabbit on the stove.
不是的
No.
然而我们都错过了一段良缘了
But I think we've both missed a great opportunity here.
再见
Bye.
(伯纳与莉蒂亚之喜宴)
(三个月后)
妈的！
Oh, fuck!
妈的
Fuck.
妈的 见他妈的鬼
Fuck. Fuckity fuck.
该死，妈的！
Fuck. Fuck!
-开车还是坐计程车？ -计程车吧，找不到停车位的
- Car or taxi? - Taxi. We could never park.
还是开车好一点
Car seems a good idea.
-妈的 -妈的
- Fuck. - Fuck.
别管它，没有人注意到的
Leave it. No one will notice.
这次…
Well...
对不起，我迟到了，堵车
...sorry I'm late. Traffic.
是的
Yeah.
今天是谁结婚呢？
Who is it today?
再照一张
One more, quick.
他们准备好了
They're ready to go.
因父
In the name of the Father...
及子
...and of the Son...
及圣灵之命，阿们
...and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.
大家一起祈祷
Let us pray.
天父，你把婚姻的缔结 变为神圣的神秘
Father, you have made the bond of marriage a holy mystery...
象征基督对教会的爱
...a symbol of Christ's love for his church.
请你透过儿子主耶稣基督
Hear our prayers for Bernard and Lydia...
垂听我们为伯纳和莉蒂亚的祷告
...through your son, Jesus Christ, our lord...
他与你一起统治大地
...who lives and reigns with you...
及圣山羊…
...and the Holy goat.
圣灵
Ghost.
唯一及永在的真神，阿们
One God, forever and ever. Amen.
首次主持婚礼 他是这家人的朋友
It's his first time. He's a friend of the family.
-太好了 -伯纳和莉蒂亚
- Excellent. - Bernard and Lydia...
我要询问你们 是否愿意承担婚姻的义务
...I shall now ask if you freely undertake the obligations of marriage.
伯纳，请你跟我说一遍
Bernard, repeat after me:
我庄严地宣告
I do solemnly declare...
没任何法律上的障碍
...that I know not of any lawful impediment...
妨碍我，莉蒂亚…
...why I, Lydia...
妨碍我，伯纳…
...why I, Bernard...
对不起
Sorry.
我…
Why I...
伯纳葛佛瑞圣约翰德莱尼
...Bernard Godfrey Saint John Delaney...
我，伯纳杰佛瑞辛约翰德莱尼
Why I, Bernard Geoffrey Sinjin Delaney...
跟莉蒂亚约翰希博特
...may not be joined in matrimony...
结为夫妇
...to Lydia John Hibbott.
跟莉蒂亚琼希博特
...may not be joined in matrimony...
结为夫妇
...to Lydia Jane Hibbott.
莉蒂亚
Lydia...
请你跟我说一遍
...repeat after me:
我庄严地宣告
I do solemnly declare...
没任何法律上的障碍
...that I know not of any lawful impediment...
妨碍我，莉蒂亚琼希博特
...why I, Lydia Jane Hibbott...
下『蛋』给…
...may not be johned in matrimony...
下嫁给…
...may not be joined in matrimony...
伯纳杰佛瑞
...to Bernard Geoffrey...
辛约翰德莱尼
...Sijern... Sijin Delaney.
伯纳…
...to Bernard...
杰佛瑞…
...Geoffrey...
辛约翰德莱尼
...Sinjin Delaney.
我请在坐各位见证
I call upon those persons here present to witness...
我，伯纳
...that I, Bernard...
德莱尼
...Delaney...
我，伯纳德莱尼
...that I, Bernard Delaney...
愿意娶你，莉蒂亚琼希博特
...do take thee, Lydia Jane Hibbott...
为我的『可怕』妻子
...to be my awful wedded wife.
为我的合法妻子
...to be my lawful wedded wife.
对…对极了
That's r... That's right.
愿全能的天父祝福你们
May almighty God bless you all.
因父、及子、及圣零…圣灵之名
The Father, the Son and the Holy spigot... Spirit.
阿们
Amen.
好极了！
Bravo!
谢谢
Thanks.
-我们来了 -这边！
- We're coming, Bernie. - Up here!
对不起
Sorry.
对不起…
Sorry. Sorry.
这边？当然了
That way? Yes, of course.
-对不起，你们两个… -汤姆，别动
- Sorry. Could you two...? - Tom, don't go away.
对不起
Sorry.
我对婚姻有一个新理论
I've got a new theory about marriage.
两个相爱的人同居，突然间…
Two people are in love, they live together, and then suddenly...
一天他们相对无言
...one day they run out of conversation.
连一个话题都找不到
Totally. They can't think of a single thing to say to each other.
就是这样，惊惶失措
That's it. Panic.
然后突然之间
Then suddenly...
他们想出了打破僵局的方法
...it occurs to the chap that there is a way out of the deadlock.
-是什么？ -他向她求婚
- Which is? - He'll ask her to marry him.
英明！真英明！
Brilliant. Brilliant!
他们这辈子都有话可说了
They've got something to talk about for the rest of their lives.
婚姻是解决无话可说的方法
You're saying marriage is a way to get out of a pause in conversation.
是打破僵局的灵丹妙药
The definitive icebreaker.
汤姆，演讲的内容是什么？
Tom, how's the speech coming along?
我想是很不错的，老少咸宜
It's pretty good, I think. Something for everyone.
笑中有泪
Tears, laughter.
好极了
Excellent.
这个理论非常好
I think it's a very good theory, Gareth.
有些人却认为结婚 是因为有真爱
There is another argument that it has something to do with true love.
这也是一种见解
Now there's a thought.
有什么可以效劳的地方？
Can I help you, sir?
麻烦你给我三杯白兰地
Can I have three glasses of brandy, please?
你好
Hi.
- Hello. - How are you?
你好吗？
很好
Fine. Fine.
对不起，见到你实在太高兴了
Yeah. Sorry, I'm overwhelmed to see you.
请你别再回美国去了
Look, don't go back to America. Please.
-我很快回来，知道吗？ -好的
- Be back in two secs, okay? - Okay.
菲欧娜
Hi, Fi.
这是你们的，五小时后见
That's yours and yours. See you in 5 hours.
-出了状况吗？ -对，这个婚礼真是棒呆了
- Something happened? - Yes. This is a bloody great wedding.
你好
Hi.
你看起来很完美 其实也许你天生完美
Well, you look perfect. In fact, you probably are perfect.
-你近来好吗？ -真的很好
- Well, how are you? - I'm really well.
查尔斯，他是我的未婚夫哈米什
Charles, I'd like you to meet Hamish, my fiance.
太好了
Excellent.
你好吗？哈米什，很高兴认识你
How do you do, Hamish? Delighted to meet you.
很高兴见到嘉莉返回英国
Charming to find Carrie back here.
我可是费尽唇舌的呢
It took lots of persuading.
走吧，我对詹姆士说带了你来
Come on, darling, I told James I was getting you.
他会想我已经拿你没法了
He'll think I've totally lost control over you already.
待会见
I'll see you later.
你还好吧？
How are you doing, Charles?
突然之间就不好了
Not great, actually, suddenly.
我不知道
I don't know.
我的意思是…
I mean...
我干嘛老是参加婚礼…
What the hell's going on here? Why am I always at weddings...
而新郎总不是我？
...and never actually getting married, Matt?
也许是因为你有点邋遢
It's probably because you're a bit scruffy.
对
Yeah.
或是因为你还没碰到意中人
Or it could also be because you haven't met the right girl.
就是这样吗？
But you see, is that it?
也许其实我经常都碰到意中人
Maybe I have met the right girls. Maybe I meet them all the time.
-可能问题在我身上 -胡说
- Maybe it's me. - Oh, nonsense.
各位先生、女士
My lords, ladies and gentlemen...
晚餐已经准备好了
...dinner is served.
可能你会在晚宴上找到妻子呢
Come on. Odds on you meet your wife at dinner.
对
Yes.
天啊
Oh, my God.
查尔斯？
Charles?
你好
Hi.
-你好，我是阿利斯泰尔 -你好
- Hello, I'm Alistair. - Great.
你认识薇洛妮卡的
And I believe you know Veronica.
对，你好，薇
Yeah. Hi, V.
妮基
Nicki.
真好
Great.
你结婚了吗？
Tell me, are you married?
还没
No.
你是同性恋的吗？
Are you a lesbian?
老天爷！
Good lord!
你为何会这么说的呢？
Well, what made you say that?
这是女人独身的可能性之一
It's one of the possibilities for unmarried girls.
总比说找不到意中人
It's a bit more interesting than saying:
来得有趣吧
"Oh, dear. Just never found the right chap."
对
Quite right.
开心就好，不是吗？
Why be dull?
谢谢
Thank you.
事实上，我早已有意中人 只是他不爱我
The truth is, I have met the right person, only he's not in love with me.
在我不再爱他之前，没人有机会
Until I stop loving him, no one stands a chance.
真倒霉
Bad luck.
可不是吗？
Yes, isn't it?
我念书时曾经是同性恋者
I was a lesbian once at school...
只当了十五分钟，该不算数吧
...but only for 15 minutes. I don't think it counts.
茶叶一共有四百多种
There are 400 different kinds of tea...
还不包括所谓的水果茶在内
...and that's not including all these so-called fruit teas.
我曾带薇到印度参观茶园
I took Veronica to India to look at the plantations.
好极了
Excellent.
你曾和她游印度吧
I believe you and her went there once.
是的
That's right.
查尔斯讨厌透了
Charles was vile.
我快要吐了，他却坚持说笑话
He insisted on cracking jokes while I was ill.
我只想使你振作起来
I was cheering you up.
原来你就是那个薇洛妮卡！
You're that Veronica!
哪个薇洛妮卡呢？
Which Veronica?
查理？
Charlie?
记得孟买吗？
Remember Bombay?
我跟查理约会时
When Charles and I were going out, he told me he'd had...
他说他跟『呕吐的薇』
...this interesting journey around India...
在印度有一次有趣的旅程呢 大概是如此吧
...with Vomiting Veronica. I think that was it.
我也记不起自己说过了 也许有吧
I don't remember ever mentioning it. Maybe I did.
查尔斯
Oh, come on, Charles.
你是我约会过的人中 最轻率的了
I don't think I've been out with anyone less discreet.
你说得有点夸张了
That's a bit of an exaggeration.
才不是呢
It is not.
我记得你说过一个叫海伦娜的？
I remember you going on about this girl. Helena, was it?
她妈妈向你献殷勤
Her mother made a pass at you.
我记得这个呢！
I remember this!
你不知道若不接受她 是否于礼不合呢！
You couldn't work out if it would be impolite not to accept her advances!
对！
That's right!
海伦娜是猪小姐 她妈妈就是猪太太
Helena was Miss Piggy, so her mother was Mrs. Piggy.
也许…
I think perhaps it was...
从那时起，我们已经瘦了很多
We've both lost a lot of weight since then.
真好，要演讲了
Great. The speeches.
各位尊贵的先生、女士
My lords, ladies and gentlemen...
请静听伴郎致词
...pray silence for the best man.
伯纳跟我说她跟莉蒂亚订婚时
When Bernard told me he was getting engaged to Lydia...
我恭喜他，因为他其他的女友
...I congratulated him because all his other girlfriends...
实在是蹩脚货
...had been such complete dogs.
其中大部分都是今晚的坐上客
May I say we are delighted to have so many of them here this evening.
看见卡密拉，我特别高兴
I'm particularly delighted to see Camilla...
你们都可能记得
...who many of you will probably remember...
她是伯纳第一个求婚对象
...as the first person Bernard asked to marry him.
若我没记错，她叫他滚蛋
If I remember rightly, she told him to sod off.
这倒是莉蒂亚的福气
And lucky for Lydia that she did.
真教人失望
It's very disappointing.
全场最标致的美女在我那一桌 叫嘉莉
We had the most adorable girl at our table called Carrie.
她未婚夫似乎很富有 拥有半个苏格兰呢
Apparently her fiance's awfully grand, and he owns half of Scotland.
-你怎么了？ -我被困在见鬼的婚礼里
- How are you? - I'm stuck in the wedding from hell.
前任女友的阴魂缠绕不散
Ghosts of girlfriends past at every turn.
若再遇上汉莉雅塔 噩梦就完成了
If I see Henrietta, the horror will be complete.
查尔斯
Hello, Charles.
汉，你好吗？
Hello, Hen. How are you?
汉，我…
Oh, Hen, l...
你干嘛就是不肯放过她呢？
Why can't you leave her alone?
你还伤得她不够吗？
Haven't you hurt her enough?
失陪了 我还是躲到别人不到的地方去吧
Excuse me. I think I'd better be where other people are not.
你好
Hello.
我是塞雷纳
你好
我还在学习
也许会错误『白』『初』
不，很好…
-你想跳舞吗？ -好
好『猪』意
计程车！
Taxi!
晚安
Good night, sir.
谢谢
Thank you.
我知道，没事的，太好了
I know. It's all right. Oh, God, this is wonderful.
求求你
Please.
等等，这样不好玩 我要看看我丈夫！
Oh, wait a minute. This is no fun. I want to see my lovely husband!
谁是坏坏的新郎呢？
Who's a very bad bridegroom, indeed?!
-你有男朋友吗？ -有
- Have you got a boyfriend? - Yes.
-他叫什么名字？ -杜夫，擅长打乒乓球
- What's his name? - Dolph. He's good at table tennis.
你呢？
What about you?
没有
No. Afraid not.
为什么呢？
Why not?
不知道
I don't know.
因为我爱慕的人…
Because most of the blokes I fancy...
都觉得我是傻瓜，姿色又平庸
...think I'm stupid and pointless...
他们干过我之后就丢下我
...and so they just bonk me and then leave me.
那些喜欢我的人，简直是讨厌鬼
And the kind of blokes that do fancy me, I think are drips.
我连干他们的劲儿都没有
I can't even be bothered to bonk them...
所以现在我一无所有
...which does sort of leave me a bit nowhere.
什么是『干』呢？
What's bonking?
跟打乒乓球差不多
Well, it's kind of like table tennis...
只是所用的『球』比较小一点
...only with slightly smaller balls.
正点！
So good!
我爱老婆！
I love my wife!
我爱老公！
And I love my husband!
我们还是回去吧
Think we'd better be getting back?
也许可以多等几分钟 再来一个回合
Or we could just wait a few minutes and have another go.
你好坏…
Naughty...
坏透的家伙
...naughty little rabbit.
我找到了
Found it.
查尔斯，我们得聊聊
Charles. Charles, we must talk.
对…
Right. You're right.
事实上，我跟很多人说起你
The thing is, Charlie, I've spoken to lots of people about you.
大家都同意你有问题
And everybody agrees you're in real trouble, Charles.
是吗？
Am I?
你每段的关系都很短暂
You see, you're turning into a serial monogamist.
女友如走马灯般，但你谁也不爱
One girl after another, yet you'll never love anyone...
因为你不让她们接近你
...because you never let them near you.
正好相反
On the contrary, Hen...
你对大家总是那么温柔体贴
You're affectionate to them and sweet to them.
虽然你觉得我是笨蛋 还是对我那么好
Even to me, although you thought I was an idiot.
-我没有 -你有
- I did not. - You did.
我以为U2合唱团是潜艇种类
I thought U2 was a type of submarine.
他们的音乐确有海洋的质素
Well, their music has a naval quality.
我说真的，你得给别人机会
Be serious, Charles. You must give people a chance.
你不用逼迫自己结婚
You don't have to think, "I must get married."
但不能以一定不结婚的心态 去谈恋爱
But you mustn't start relationships thinking, "I mustn't get married."
很多时候我什么都没想 我只是消磨时间而已
Most of the time I don't think at all. I just potter along.
查尔斯！
Oh, Charlie!
天啊，你从前看着我的眼神！
Oh, God, the way you used to look at me!
是我误会了而已
I just misread it, that's all.
我以为你要求婚 原来你却在想如何离开我
I thought you were going to propose... ...and you were working out how to leave.
我没有
No, no. I wasn't.
天啊，实在太荒谬了
Oh, God. This is ridiculous.
-汉… -不要
- Hen... - No.
不要，汉！…
No, Hen! Hen!
不要！
No!
过得愉快吗？
Having a good night?
很好
Yes, yes.
娱乐价值跟老爸的葬礼 不相上下
It's right up there with my father's funeral for sheer entertainment value.
还以为你已经离开了
I thought you'd gone.
哈米什要赶火车回爱丁堡
No. Hamish has to take the Edinburgh sleeper.
我走了，要送我一程吗？
I'm off now. Keep me company?
这里可以了
Here, please.
要上来喝杯睡前酒吗？
You want to come up for a nightcap?
你确定？
You sure?
对，我们可以冒这个险
Yes. I think we can risk it.
我蛮确定自己可以抗拒你 你又不是那么帅
I'm pretty sure I can resist you. You're not that cute.
对不起，好主意
Sorry. Yeah, great.
早安，查尔斯
早餐准备好了
Breakfast's up.
(一个月后)
烤得有点焦
Well, it's a bit burnt.
太好了
Excellent.
你今天要忙什么呢？
What are you up to today?
对
Oh, yeah.
今天是我这辈子 首个不用参加婚礼的周末
I'm taking advantage of the fact that for the first time in my life...
我要好好利用它
...it's Saturday, and I don't have a wedding to go to.
我约了大卫，只要不迟到就行
All I have to do is not be late for David.
我要找工作
I'm gonna go for a job.
一间叫劲爆的店要找店员
A shop called Spank wants a sales assistant.
很适合我的
I think I'd be great.
那里出售稀奇古怪的保险套
They sell all this funny rubber stuff.
不好
Oh, no.
又是结婚请柬
Another wedding invitation...
还有礼单，真好
...and a list. Lovely.
人们说只有性变态的 才用保险套
Well, they say rubber's mainly for perverts.
我不知道为什么，它蛮实用的
I don't know why. It's very practical, actually.
液体沾上去，它就会脱落
You spill anything on it, and it just comes off.
所以变态的才喜欢吧
I suppose that could be why the perverts like it.
你还好吧？
You all right?
还好
Yeah, yeah.
是嘉莉，记得
It's that girl, Carrie. You remember...
那个美国女郎
...the American.
对不起，打扰你了
Excuse me. Sorry to interrupt.
有没有班克斯夫妇的礼单呢？
Do you have the wedding list for Banks?
当然有
Certainly, sir.
有许多一千镑左右的选择 about the ￡1000 mark.
Lots of beautiful things for around
有没有价值五十镑的东西？ 多不多？ ￡50 mark? Is there much?
What about, things around the sort of
你可以买那个侏儒战士像
Well, you could get that pygmy warrior over there.
这个吗？太好了
This? Excellent.
余下的3，950镑就由别人捐助吧 the other ￡3950.
If you could find someone to chip in
我们的购物袋才一镑半一个 are ￡1.50 each.
Or our carrier bags
你买33个，不就成了吗？
Why don't you just get 33 of them?
我还是不要了
Yes, well, I think I'll probably leave it.
谢谢你，你真的很…
Thanks very much. You've been very...
你买了什么呢？
What'd you get?
你吓坏我了！
Blimey!
我没有呢
Well, I never.
还没有，我还在考虑
Nothing yet. I'm just, you know, deciding.
见到你真好
It's nice to see you.
收礼物实在太棒了
This present thing is great.
我早该在多年前就结婚了
I should've gotten married years ago.
有没有人要买侏儒像？
Did anybody go for the pygmy?
这位年轻人正想买下来
The young man was thinking about it.
不用了！
Oh, no!
你送我烟灰缸就行了
Just get me an ashtray.
这半小时你有空吗？
Are you free for about a half-hour?
我本约了弟弟，但可以迟一点
Yeah. I'm supposed to meet my brother, but I can be a bit late.
好，跟我来 你得作出重要的抉择
Good, come with me. You have an important decision to make.
最重要的是你不能笑
It's crucial that you mustn't laugh.
好的
Okay, right.
你觉得怎么样呢？
What do you think?
好极了
Divine.
像棉花糖？
Bit of a meringue?
别担心，我们才刚开始而已
Oh, don't worry. We've only just begun.
你觉得呢？
What do you think?
开玩笑
- You're kidding. - It would be wonderful, wouldn't it?
很棒吧，是不是？ 留待下次吧
Maybe next time.
你觉得怎么样？
What do you think?
我早料到
I knew it.
只要配一根拐杖 你就可以牧羊了
But with a staff, you could mind sheep.
你不得无礼
Don't be rude.
这件蛮性感的
It's a bit sexy, this.
这个…
Well...
若我是你丈夫，定会自豪死了
...if I were your husband, I would die of pride.
对，有危险
You're right. It is dangerous.
没什么比勃起的神父更倒胃口
There's nothing more off-putting than a priest with an enormous erection.
一想起你不会再跟别人睡 感觉很奇怪
One strange thing is thinking you'll never sleep with anyone else.
你不会不忠吗？
You don't think you'll be unfaithful?
结了婚之后就不会
No. Not once I'm married.
我跟哈米什说若他敢胡来 我会干掉他，所以我也不能胡来
I told Hamish I'll kill him if he does, so I better stick to that.
有道理
Quite right.
反正我也疯够了
Anyway, I reckon I've had my fair run at it.
你觉得什么才算是疯够？
What is a fair run these days down your way?
不知道
Oh, I don't know.
不只一个吧
More than one.
来吧
Well, come on.
告诉我
Tell me.
我已经看过那婚纱 我们没有秘密了
I've seen the dress. We have no secrets now.
好吧
Well...
第一个
The first one...
当然是很难忘的，他很好
...of course, not easily forgotten, was kind of nice.
第二个的背部长毛
Two: hairy back.
第三、四、五…
Three, four, five...
第六个是我生日 在父母的房间里
Six was on my birthday in my parents' room.
-哪个生日？ -十七岁
- Which birthday? - 17th.
我们才满十七岁啊？
We've only reached 17?
我在郊外长大 经常在干草堆打滚
I grew up in the country. Lots of rolling around in haystacks.
好，第七个
Okay, seven.
第八个，很不幸，把我吓怀了
Eight, unfortunately, was quite a shock.
第九个，在篱笆上干，很辛苦 别试
Nine: against a fence. Very uncomfortable. Don't try it.
我不会
I won't.
第十个好极了，像在天堂一样
Ten was gorgeous. Just heaven, just...
太美妙了
He was wonderful.
我讨厌他
I hate him.
第十一个在第十个之后 当然会教人失望
Eleven: obviously, after 10, disappointing.
12至17是大学时代的事
Twelve through 17: the university years.
细心、体贴又聪明的男孩子 在性爱方面是笨蛋
Sensitive, caring, intelligent boys. Sexually speaking, a real low patch.
第18个伤透了我的心
Eighteen broke my heart.
好几年也不能忘怀他
Years of yearning.
我很难过
I'm sorry.
20，天啊，竟然数了20个
Twenty... Oh, my God, I can't believe I've reached 20.
第21个的舌头很大
Twenty-one: elephant tongue.
第22个不断打瞌睡 那是我来英国的第一年
Twenty-two kept falling asleep. That was my first year in England.
抱歉
I do apologize.
第23跟24个是一起来的
Twenty-three and 24 together.
-很了不起吧 -你说真的吗？
- That was something. - Seriously?
第27个是个错误
Twenty-seven. Now that was a mistake.
第27个才突然间出错？
Suddenly, at 27, you make a mistake?
对，他不断尖叫
Well, yes, he kept screaming.
我的胃口尽失 几乎从此鸣金收兵
It was very off-putting. I nearly gave up on the whole thing.
可是史宾杜改变了我的想法 他是第28个
But Spencer changed my mind. That's 28.
他的爸爸是第29个
His father, 29.
他爸爸？
His father?
三十…
Thirty...
31，天啊！
Thirty-one, oh, my God.
第32个很美好
Thirty-two was lovely.
然后是我的未婚夫 他是第33个
And then my fiance. That's 33.
厉害！
Wow!
我在你未婚夫之后吗？
So I came after your fiance?
不，你是第32个
No, you were 32.
就这么多
So there you go.
比玛丹娜少，比黛妃多 希望是吧
Less than Madonna, more than Princess Di, I hope.
你跟多少人睡过呢？
And you? How many have you slept with?
天啊，完全不能相比
Christ. Nothing like that many.
真不知道我的时间花了在哪
I don't know what the fuck I've been doing with my time, actually.
对，是工作，我经常加班
Work, yeah, that's it, work. I have been working late a lot.
但愿我有打电话给你
I wish I'd rung you...
但是你却没有打电话给我
...but then you never rang me.
你真残忍，无情的跟我睡过两次 却从不打电话给我
You ruthlessly slept with me twice and never rang me.
见鬼！
Oh, bollocks!
帮帮我，求求你！
Help me, please. Please.
你不再是我哥哥了 你只是一个我认识的饭桶
对不起
嘉莉，他是我弟弟大卫 她是嘉莉
Carrie, this is David, my brother.
你好
Hi.
刚才我替她挑结婚礼服
愚蠢的藉口，她要嫁给谁？
老淫贼
怎么样的老淫贼 能娶这样的如花美眷？
我说你要嫁给哈米什
I was just telling him about you marrying Hamish...
他说他是一等的好人
...and he said it couldn't have happened to a nicer fellow.
你跟她不是有一腿的吗？
-你在哪结婚？ -苏格兰
- Where are you doing it? - Scotland.
对
胸脯真美
他说那里的风景优美，山峦起伏
He says that's a beautiful place. Hilly.
你也来参加婚礼吧
You should come to the wedding too.
我希望有多些朋友来 免得全是哈米什的朋友
I want many friends there to make up for the stiffs that Hamish knows.
你进去吧
Well, you better go in.
再见
Bye.
-再见 -再见
- Bye. - Bye.
走吧，迟到了
妈的
Fuck it.
听着
Look. Sorry, sorry.
对不起
我只是…这个问题很笨
I just, well... This is a really stupid question...
尤其是在购物之旅之后
...particularly in view of our recent shopping excursion.
我只是纳闷，万一…
But, I just wondered if by any chance...
当然不会 我是只跟九个人睡过的蠢货
Obviously not, because I'm a git who's only slept with nine people.
但是，我只是纳闷…
But I just wondered...
我真的觉得…
I really feel...
总之，我以大卫卡西迪的话
In short, to recap in a slightly clearer version...
摘要地说一篇
...in the words of David Cassidy, in fact...
他在『鹧鸪家族』中写着
...while he was with The Partridge Family...
我想我爱你
...I think I love you.
我只是纳闷万一你不想…
I just wondered whether by any chance you wouldn't like to...
不…当然不会
No, no, no. Of course not.
我是笨蛋，他不是
I'm an idiot, he's not.
好极…了不起
Excellent. Excellent. Fantastic.
很高兴再见你，打扰你了 我要走了
Lovely to see you. Sorry to disturb. Better get on.
妈的！
Fuck!
真的很浪漫
That was very romantic.
我仔细考虑过的，我不想做错
Well, I thought it over a lot. I wanted to get it just right.
最重要的是说出来了
Important to have said it, I think.
你究竟要说什么？
Said what, exactly?
说了…
Said...
我刚才在说…
...you know, what I just said about...
大卫卡西迪
...David Cassidy.
你很可爱
You're lovely.
(哈米什与嘉莉之喜宴)
(一个月后)
婚姻是为夫妇间终身的爱恋
It was ordained for lifelong faithful relationship of conjugal love.
以及人类社会的福祉而制定的
It was ordained for the welfare of human society...
只有认真对待婚姻关系
...which can be strong and happy...
社会才能强大与快乐
...only when the marriage bond is held in honor.
这对新人…
Into this holy estate...
渴望踏入这个神圣的人生阶段
...these two persons now desire to enter.
因此若有人可以提出
Wherefore if anyone can show any just cause...
他们不能结为合法夫妇的原因
...why they may not lawfully be joined together in marriage...
请马上提出来
...let him now declare it.
对不起
Sorry.
请说吧
Please rise.
哈米什
Do you, Hamish...
你愿意娶卡洛林为妻子吗？
...take this woman, Caroline, to be your wedded wife?
你是否愿意在上帝和来宾面前
And do you, in the presence of God and before this congregation...
承诺当一个忠诚的丈夫
...promise and covenant to be to her, a loving and faithful husband...
至死不渝？
...until God shall separate you by death?
我愿意
I do.
卡洛林
Do you, Caroline...
你愿意嫁给哈米什？
...take this man, Hamish, to be your wedded husband?
并在上帝和来宾的面前
And do you, in the presence of God and before this congregation...
承诺当一个忠诚的妻子
...promise and covenant to be to him a loving and faithful wife...
至死不渝？
...until God shall separate you by death?
我愿意
I do.
见他奶奶的鬼
Fuck-a-doodle-doo.
-很高兴见到你 -见到你真好
- Awfully nice to meet you. - Nice to meet you.
你好吗？
How do you do?
你好
Hello.
你很漂亮
You look beautiful.
-不像棉花糖 -谢了
- Not a meringue in sight. - Thanks.
天啊
Blimey.
是苏格兰舞呢！
It's Brigadoon. It's bloody Brigadoon!
朋友们，你知道
Dear old things, as you know...
我一向都为大家是单身贵族 而自豪
...I've always been proud there isn't a wedding ring between the lot of us.
随着岁月的流逝 我开始感到苦恼
Over the passing of years, it's suddenly beginning to distress me.
我想换个口味 参加好朋友的婚礼
I'd like to go to the wedding of someone I really loved, for a change.
别怪我 我已经向所有认识的人求婚
Don't blame me. I've asked practically everyone I know.
你没有问我
You haven't asked me.
-没有吗？ -没有
- Haven't I? - No.
思嘉
Oh, Scarlett.
你想嫁给我吗？
Would you like to?
不，谢了，感激你问我
No, thank you. It was very nice of you to ask.
别客气
Well, anytime.
对，汤姆，精神可嘉
Quite right, Tom. That's the spirit.
这是你们今晚的命令
Tonight, these are your orders:
四出觅侣，找个丈夫或妻子
Go forth and conjugate. Find husbands and wives.
好计划，你觉得怎么样？
Excellent plan. What do you think, Fifi?
在人群中寻找未来丈夫？
Spot a potential hubby in the throng?
-走开吧 -对
- Bugger off, Tom. - Quite right.
打仗之前，先来祝酒吧
A toast before we go into battle.
为真爱干杯
To true love.
无论爱情以何种姿态降临
In whatever shape or form it may come.
但愿我们在老迈时 都能自豪地说：
May we all in our dotage be proud to say:
『从前也有人倾慕我呢』
"I was adored once too."
-为真爱干杯 -为真爱干杯！
- True love. - True love!
大部分的人…
Apparently, an enormous number of people...
都会在婚礼上邂逅将来的配偶
...actually bump into their future spouses at weddings.
真是有趣
Which is interesting.
我也是在婚礼上认识我丈夫的
Yes, I met my husband at a wedding.
我的酒喝光了，失陪
Good lord, I seem to have finished my drink. If you'll excuse me.
你好，我叫思嘉
Hello. My name's Scarlett.
跟郝思嘉同名，却简单多了
Named after Scarlett O'Hara, but much less trouble.
你叫什么名字呢？
What's your name?
我叫瑞德
My name's Rhett.
不是吧 不是！
No. Not really!
不是的，我叫贾斯特
No, not really. In fact, it's Chester.
你真会开玩笑
You kidder.
我一直幻想美国人是呆子
I always imagine Americans are going to be dull as shit.
当然你不是了
I mean, of course you're not, are you?
史帝夫马丁也是美国人吧？
Steve Martin's American, isn't he?
是的
Yes, he is.
你很可爱
You're lovely.
来吧！
Come on!
查尔斯
Hello, Charles.
汉，你好
Oh, Hen. Hi.
对不起，我今天不能再受刺激
I'm sorry. I couldn't really bear a scene today.
我知道我们有很多话要说
I know we probably got tons to talk about.
上次我真是那么糟糕吗？
Did I behave that atrociously last time?
-记得惊魂记中的出浴场面吗？ -记得
Remember the shower scene in Psycho?
Yeah.
比那个更可怕
Scarier.
我很沮丧，你好吗？
Oh, God, I'm depressed, Hen. How are you?
我很高兴，像在云端飘荡
I'm cheerful, actually. I weigh almost nothing.
我还找到很棒的新男朋友呢
And I've got a divine new boyfriend.
-也许我们应该结婚 -天啊，不要
- Perhaps we should've married. - Good God, no.
我得嫁给你的朋友 我受不了菲欧娜
I'd have had to marry your friends. I'm not quite sure I could take Fiona.
菲欧娜喜欢你的
Fiona loves you.
她叫我做鸭子脸
Fiona calls me duckface.
我从没听过
Well, I never heard that.
改天吃午饭吧
Look, darling, come to lunch soon.
打电话给我，还是那么帅！
Give me a ring, okay? Oh, still cute!
鸭子脸怎么了？
How's duckface?
状态不俗，不算太疯狂了
Good form, actually. Not too mad.
各位先生、女士
Ladies and gentlemen...
新娘和新郎出来了
...the bride and groom.
你喜欢那个女孩吧？
You like this girl, don't you?
是的
Yes.
Yes, it's a...
终于发生了，感觉很奇怪
Well, it's a strange thing when at last it happens.
而且…
And...
她要嫁为人妇
...she's marrying someone else.
你呢？菲菲
How about you, Fifi?
找到终生伴侣了吗？
You identified a future partner for life yet?
没这个必要
No need, really.
我早已找到了
The deed is done.
多年来，我一直爱着一个人
I've been in love with the same bloke for ages.
是吗？
Have you?
他是谁呢？
Who's that?
你，查尔斯
You, Charlie.
一直都是你
It's always been you.
自我们相识之始
Since first we met...
已经是很多年前的事了
...oh so many years ago.
一开始我就知道了
I knew the first moment.
在那间拥挤的房间里
Across a crowded room.
其实是在草地上
Or lawn, in fact.
没关系吧
Doesn't matter.
我们都无能为力，这就是人生
There's nothing either of us can do. Such is life.
做朋友…
Friends isn't...
也不错，知道吗？ 有朋友也蛮不错的
...bad, you know? Friends is quite something.
菲菲
Oh, Fi.
Fi.
并不容易面对，是吗？
It's not all easy, is it?
不是
No.
忘了这件事吧
Just forget this business. Not to be.
马修
Matthew, darling.
盖瑞夫在哪？
Where's Gareth?
拿美国人开玩笑
Torturing Americans.
他真有心
How thoughtful of him.
你真的认识王尔德的吗？
Do you actually know Oscar Wilde?
我不认识他本人
Not personally, no.
但我可以给你他的传真号码
But I do know someone who could get his fax number for you.
我们跳舞吧？
Shall we dance?
有人成功戴上戒指吗？
Well, any rings on fingers?
盖瑞夫，你不晓得自己多走运
Oh, Gareth, you don't know how lucky you are.
寻找结婚对象是很棘手的
Finding someone to marry is a very tricky business.
外边很烦，马修被一个 明尼苏达州的教徒苦缠不放
It's hell out there. Matthew's trapped with a Minnesotan evangelist.
耶稣基督，把他身上的魔鬼驱走！
Come down, sweet Jesus, and cast out the devil!
各位尊贵的先生、女士
My lords, ladies, and gentlemen...
请把酒杯注满
...please charge your glasses.
首先，罕见地，有请新娘出场
First, and rather unusually, we have the bride.
好极了，我喜欢这个女孩
Excellent. I love this girl.
谢谢
Thank you.
我要感谢从美国远道而来的人
I'd like to thank all of you who flew in from the States.
我很感动
I'm really touched.
对其他人来说 有很多可怕的美国人来到
For you others, I'd have thought lots of frightful Americans flying in...
可能是不出席的原因 所以我也感激你
...was an excuse for staying away, so I thank you too.
若家父今天在场的话
If my darling dad had been here today...
现在他会发言
...he would have been speaking now.
他一定会说：『婚纱很漂亮』
I know he would have said, "Great dress, babe...
『但你为何要嫁给 穿裙子的古董呢？』
...but why in the hell are you marrying the stiff in the skirt?"
我的答案会跟现在一样
And I would have given him the same answer that I give you:
『因为我爱他』
"Because I love him."
跟爸同年去世的约翰蓝侬曾说
As John Lennon said, who died the same year as my dad:
『爱就是答案』
"Love is the answer.
『你是清楚知道的』
And you know that for sure."
还有一件事
One more thing:
有人跟我说，若我的婚姻有问题
Someone told me here, that if things with Hamish didn't work out...
他愿意干涉，谢了 我会告诉你的
...that he'd step in. So thanks, and I'll keep you posted.
说得好！
Bravo!
各位，有请哈米什班克斯爵士
And now, my lords, ladies and gentlemen, Sir Hamish Banks.
任何从政超过二十年的人
Anyone involved in politics for the last 20 years...
都会习惯给女人抢镜头
...has gotten used to being upstaged by a woman.
我倒没想过在结婚日也会这样
I didn't expect it to happen to me on my wedding day.
然而，我必须说
However, I must also say...
我乐意在余生里
...that I'm quite happy to be upstaged by this woman...
都被这个女人抢镜头
...for the rest of my life.
后面有人在喝采吗？ 我们政治家也习惯了
Some barracking at the back again? Something we politicians are used to.
-糟糕，快找医生来 -对
- Shit. Find a doctor. - Right. Okay.
首先我要感谢各位女傧相
First, I want to extend my compliments to the bridesmaids.
你们非常称职
You did your duty superbly.
以后我每次结婚 都会请你们帮忙
I intend to use you every time I get married from now on.
我要谢谢在教区内
I want to thank all those wonderful ladies of the parish...
负责布置教堂的女士
...who did the flowers in the church.
令这座古旧的建筑物 今天散发出青春气息
The stern old building took on a look of flushed youth today.
记得我第一眼看见卡洛林时
I remember the first time I laid eyes on Caroline.
我想，若她患有近视的话
I thought to myself, "If by any chance she's shortsighted...
我在余生也会很快乐
...I might just be happy for the rest of my life."
我第一次看见自己的将来
I thought I could see my future for the first time.
在往后的许多年
It was a joyful one...
都充满喜乐
...for years and years to come.
因为他是个快乐人
我们大家都如是说
早安 感谢你们在这寒冷的一天来到
Good morning, and a warm welcome to you all on this cold day.
礼拜式将于几分钟后开始
Our service will begin in a few minutes.
首先我们邀请盖瑞夫的密友
But first we have asked Matthew...
马修说几句话
...Gareth's closest friend, to say a few words.
盖瑞夫喜欢葬礼多于婚礼
Gareth used to prefer funerals to weddings.
他说出席自己始终有机会 参予的场合
He said it was easier to get enthusiastic about a ceremony...
特别容易兴奋
...one had an outside chance of eventually being involved in.
为了准备演词 我打电话给很多人
In order to prepare this speech, I rang people to get a general picture...
看看别人对盖瑞夫的印象
...of how Gareth was regarded by those who met him.
胖是人们最常挂在嘴边的字
"Fat" seems to have been a word people most connected with him.
非常粗鲁也很受大家欢迎
"Terribly rude" also rang a lot of bells.
肥胖粗野是陌生人对他的观感
"So very fat and very rude" seems to have been the stranger's viewpoint.
另一方面，有些人致电给我 说很喜爱他
On the other hand, some of you have rung me to say that you loved him...
若他听见了，一定会很兴奋
...which I know he would have been thrilled to hear.
你们记得他的殷勤招待
You remember his fabulous hospitality.
他那实验性烹饪方法
His strange experimental cooking.
幸好那张香蕉鸭的食谱
The recipe for duck a la banana...
会跟他一起长埋黄土
...fortunately goes with him to his grave.
最重要的是
Most of all...
你们说起他是异常快乐的人
...you tell me of his enormous capacity for joy.
他最高兴的时候
And when joyful...
就是酩酊大醉的时候
When joyful, for highly vocal drunkenness.
但我希望你们会记着 他快乐的一面
But I hope joyful is how you will remember him.
而非在教堂里 躺在箱子中的模样
Not stuck in a box in a church.
在他的背心中挑出你喜爱的一件 记着他那个模样
Pick your favorite of his waistcoats and remember him that way.
那个最杰出
The most splendid...
精神饱满
...replete...
宽大慷慨
...big-hearted...
而事实上他的心脏最衰弱
Weak-hearted, as it turned out.
我们认识中最快乐的同性恋
- and jolly bugger most of us ever met.
你或会问，我会如何纪念他
As for me, you may ask how I will remember him.
我对他有什么感觉
What I thought of him.
遗憾地，我欲语无言
Unfortunately, there I run out of words.
请原恕我把我的感受
Forgive me if I turn from my own feelings...
借另一位杰出的同性恋者
...to the words of another splendid bugger:
奥登的话说出来
W.H. Auden.
这就是我真实的感受
This is actually what I want to say:
『把时钟停住』
Stop all the clocks
『把电话切断』
Cut off the telephone
『给狗儿一块骨头 别让它吠叫』
Prevent the dog from barking With a juicy bone
『把琴声凝住 在低沉的鼓声中』
Silence the pianos And with muffled drum
『把棺木抬出来』
Bring out the coffin
『让送葬者进来』
Let the mourners come.
『让盘旋的飞机在头上呜咽』
Let the aeroplanes circle Moaning overhead
『在天空上潦草地写着』
Scribbling on the sky the message
『他死了』
He is dead.
『在鸽子的脖子上挂上蝴蝶结』
Put crepe bows around The white necks of the public doves
『让交通警员带上黑手套』
Let traffic policemen Wear black cotton gloves.
『他是我的南北西东』
He was my North, my South, My East and West
『是我作息的意义』
My working week And my Sunday rest
『是我的日夜 欢唱谈话的内容』
My noon, my midnight, My talk, my song
『还以为爱可以天长地久』
I thought that love Would last forever:
『我错了』
I was wrong.
『繁星已经无用』
The stars are not wanted now
『把它们熄灭吧』
Put out every one
『收起月亮，掩盖骄阳』
Pack up the moon And dismantle the sun
『把海水抽干，把林木扫掉』
Pour away the ocean And sweep up the wood
『从今以后，世上再没美事』
For nothing now can ever Come to any good.
再见了
Bye, now.
我送你回家吧
I'll take you home, Scarlett.
你真有心
It's good of you to come.
一定是史上最短的蜜月期吧
Must have been the shortest honeymoon in history.
没关系，可以补度蜜月
No, it's fine. We'll do it some other time.
那次你在街上说的事
That thing you said in the street?
很抱歉
Yes. I'm sorry about that.
不，我喜欢
No, I liked it.
我喜欢你说出来
I liked you saying it.
查尔斯，我送思嘉回家，知道吗？
Charlie, I'll take Scarlett home, all right?
好的
Yeah.
菲菲
Darling Fi.
走回去吧？
Walk, Charlie?
好的，好主意
Yeah. Yeah, that would be grand.
这次跟我年轻时和吉利那次的…
Never felt like that. I mean, something vaguely similar for Jilly...
感觉很像
...when I was young.
吉利？
Jilly?
我的猎犬
Labrador.
对，很奇怪吧？
Yes, it's odd, isn't it?
我们一向为单身自豪，没想到
For years we've been single and proud and never noticed...
却忽略了当中两人 其实一直是两位一体
...that two of us were, to all intents and purposes, married all this time.
我们圈子的叛徒
Traitors in our midst.
死亡对父母来说是最难过 不是吗？
You know, in a way, I think death is hardest for the parents, don't you?
我希望可以比儿女早死
I hope I die before my children.
汤姆
Tom...
我发现了一件事
...there's one thing I find really...
你很有信心自己一定可以结婚
It's your total confidence that you will get married.
假使你没碰上心上人 那又怎么样？
I mean, what if you never find the right girl?
什么？
Sorry?
若礼拜式是有所启示的话
Surely, if that service shows anything...
那表明了世上是有完美婚姻的
...it shows that there is a perfect match.
若我们无法像 盖瑞夫和马修一样
If we can't be like Gareth and Matthew...
就只好放弃吧
...maybe we should just let it go.
我们当中有些人会独身终老
Some of us are not gonna get married.
我不知道
Well, I don't know, Charlie.
事实上，跟你不同
The truth is, unlike you...
我从不奢求触电的感觉
...I never expected the thunderbolt.
我只想认识个性和善
I always just hoped that I'd meet some nice, friendly girl...
外面又惬意的女孩
...like the look of her.
希望我的模样没叫她倒胃口
Hope the look of me didn't make her physically sick.
我提出要求
Then pop the question...
然后安定下来，快乐地生活
...and settle down and be happy.
我的父母就是这样
It worked for my parents.
除了离婚和其他麻烦之外
Well, apart from the divorce and all that.
我想至多只有六个月
I'll give you six months at the outside, Tom.
也许你说得对
Yeah, maybe you're right.
什么等待真命天子的论调
Maybe all this "waiting for one true love" stuff...
令人孤独一身
...gets you nowhere.
究竟搞什么鬼的？
What the fuck is going on?
我要确保我们不会迟到
I thought we better make absolutely sure we weren't late.
你的婚礼发型好看极了
Excellent wedding hairstyle.
(查尔斯与…)
(十个月后)
马修，世上最帅的伴郎
Matthew. The best-Iooking best man in the world.
听好…
Listen...
谢谢你
...thank you for doing this today.
别客气
Of course.
若盖瑞夫在这里就好了
I wish Gareth was here.
他也是这样想
Bet he does too.
对不起，我迟到了 其他人在停车
I'm sorry I was so late. The others are just parking the car.
我以为要跟汤姆
I thought we'd all go with Tom.
已经迟了吗？
Late? So late?
对，已是九时四十五分
Yeah, it's 9:45.
-九时四十五分？ -距离仪式开始还有45分钟
- 9:45? - Yep, 45 minutes till "I do."
该死的汤姆！ 我叫他八点整起床的
Bloody Tom! I told him to set the alarm for 8.
妈的！
Fuck it!
Fuck!
思嘉
Scarlett.
-你好 -准备好了没？
- Oh, hi. - You ready?
准备好了，给我二十秒
Absolutely. Give me 20 seconds.
-什么时候？ -要听真话吗？
- Time? - Honestly?
是的！什么时候？
Yes! Time?!
还有十分钟到九点整
About 10 to 9.
王八蛋
Bastards.
洁西卡，别再乱跳了
Jessica, stop jumping up and down, please.
一、二、三，笑一个！
One, two, three, smile!
Brilliant.
这套礼服帅死了！
This is splendid tuck.
我要说几句话
Yes, I think I might say a little word.
你们都知道 我一直观察查尔斯的恋爱生活
As many of you know, I've closely observed Charles' love life for years.
最近我开始害怕他会跟我们结婚
Recently, I'd started to despair and fear that he was married to us.
只是我们不能替他生儿育女
Apart from the fact that we won't have his babies.
我不知道
I don't know about that.
幸好，结果还是非常好
Fortunately, it's turned out splendidly.
可惜那个女孩惜神经有问题
The girl in question is sadly crazy...
不过也许这正是他爱她之处
...but perhaps that's why he loves her.
我要在这个悲痛的日子
I'd like to propose a toast to my Charlie and his beautiful girl...
敬查尔斯和他的美女
...on this tragic day.
祝你愉快，别忘记我们
So be happy and don't forget us.
谢谢
Thank you.
为查尔斯和鸭子脸干杯
To Charles and duckface.
为查尔斯和鸭子脸干杯！
To Charles and duckface!
-你觉得怎么样？ -漂亮极了
- What do you think? - You look divine.
总算成功了，不是吗？
It does work, doesn't it?
对
Yes.
感谢菲欧娜对我妻子的美言
I thank Fiona for those charming words about my future wife.
我想藉着这个机会
I'd like to take this opportunity...
读出她给你们的讯息
...to read a little message from her to you all.
真叫人兴奋
This is exciting.
她说若你们敢接近房子 她会放狗来咬你们
She says, "If any of you come near the house, I'll set the dogs on you."
说得真好
I think that's rather a nice touch.
我会放狗咬你们
"I'll set the dogs on you."
约翰，你好
John, hi.
你来了，真好
You made it. Good.
希望我的妹妹会出现吧 很少婚礼是没有新娘的
I hope me damn sister turns up. Not much of a wedding without a bride.
你没有开单身男人晚会吧
Bit of a poor show, you not having a stag night.
我们有…
We did. We did.
但在这个年纪，这并非好主意
We didn't think it was a very good idea in this day and age.
真的吗？
Really?
你今天好漂亮
Fi, you do look lovely today.
你看见我已舍弃了惯穿的黑色
Yes, as you can see I've abandoned my traditional black.
对
Yes, so you have.
从现在开始，我会穿上彩虹七色
From now on, I shall be all the colors of the rainbow...
跟喜欢我的人谈恋爱，改变一下
...and fall in love with someone who fancies me for a change.
亲爱的菲
Darling Fi.
-看 -什么？
- Look. - What?
满脸唇膏，不太好吧
Lipstick everywhere. That won't do at all.
你好
Hi. Hi.
祝你好运
Good luck.
你好，很高兴看见你来了
Hello. Glad you could come.
你好吗？
How are you?
新郎的亲属在左面 新娘的在右面
Groom's on the right. Bride's, left.
Groom on the right. Bride on the left.
天啊！
Oh, my God!
还以为你已经回德州
I thought you'd gone back to Texas.
没有你，我永不回去
Without you, never.
祝你好运
Good luck.
新郎还是新娘？
The bride or groom?
Bride or groom?
你应该很清楚，我两者都不是
It should be perfectly obvious I'm neither.
老天爷！
Great God!
女方还是男方？
Bride or groom?
女方
Bride.
好的
Yes...
好
...fine.
我觉得我是见过你的
I've got a feeling we've met before.
对，大约在二十五年前
We have. About 25 years ago.
我是你二表兄的女儿迪尔德丽 你是汤姆
I'm second cousin Harold's daughter, Deirdre. You're Tom.
老天爷！
Good lord!
-那么你我本是一家人 -对
- So you're family. - Yes.
是远亲
Only very distant.
对，当然了
Well, yes, of course.
你是新娘的亲友？
You said you were bride?
是的
Yes.
请坐吧
Well, do sit.
请坐，迪尔德丽
Do sit here, Deirdre.
天啊
Golly.
雷电交加
Thunderbolt city.
你好，马修
Hello, Matthew.
-你好，查尔斯 -你好吗？伯纳
- Hello, Charles. - Bernard, how are you?
我累坏了
Exhausted, actually.
-真好玩 -你好，莉蒂亚
- That's funny. Charles. - Hello, Lyd.
好吗？
Hi.
你很帅
You look lovely.
我一向喜欢你参加婚礼的打扮
But I always did like you dressed for weddings.
-而且还准时呢！ -对，很惊奇吧，对吗？
- And on time! - Yep! Extraordinary thing, isn't it?
哈米什好吗？
How's Hamish?
不错吧，我相信
Oh, he's fine, I believe.
你相信？
You believe?
毕竟他并非我的如意郎君
Well, yes, he wasn't the man for me after all.
你甩掉了他？
You left him?
我们彼此甩掉对方
We left each other.
是何时的事？
When?
几个月前吧
A few months now.
三月很可怕，四月更糟
March was hell. By April, it was sordid.
我不会再嫁给 年纪比我大三倍的人
That's the last time I marry someone three times my age.
查理？要开始了
Charlie? Charles, time to travel.
知道
Yeah. Yeah.
我来了
Coming. Good.
好极
Good.
你干嘛不找我呢？
So why didn't you get in touch, then?
我有想过的
I did think about it.
我也想的，只是…
I wanted to, but...
当时心情很乱
I was in a state.
我不打扰你了
So anyway, I don't want to keep you.
以后再见吧
And I'll see you afterwards.
好的，太好了
Yeah. Fine, excellent.
等等
Wait.
我带你就坐吧
I'll show you to your seat.
我带她就坐
Just showing her to her seat.
时不予我，对吗？
Our timing's been really bad, hasn't it?
真是的
It's been bad, yes.
实在是太糟了
It's been a disaster.
如你所说
It has, as you say, been...
实在是太糟了
...very bad indeed.
很高兴再见到你
God, it's lovely to see you.
祝你好运
Well, good luck.
蛮简单的
It's pretty easy.
无论谁问你 只要说我愿意就行了
Just say "I do" whenever anyone asks you a question.
可以等一下吗？
Could you just give me a sec, Matthew?
好的，去梳洗一下吧
Yes, of course. Freshen up at will.
神啊，请你饶恕我
Dear lord, forgive me for what I'm about to...
在这个神圣的地方说这句话
...say in this magnificent place of worship.
畜生！
Bugger!
畜生！…
Bugger! Bugger! Bugger!
畜生！
Bugger!
有什么地方可以效劳的呢？
Can I help at all?
没有，谢了
Huh? No. Thanks.
对不起
Sorry.
我在练声，教堂很大
Vocal exercises. Big church.
很好，我也经常这么做
Excellent. Often do the same myself.
当然不是说那个字了
Not exactly the same vocab, obviously.
通常都是说哈利路亚
Rather more hallelujahs.
我不妨碍你了
I'll leave you.
新娘来了
Bride's arriving.
好极！可是新郎却失踪了
Fabulous! We seem to have lost the groom.
把她拖住，我去找他
Stall her, and I'll see if I can find him.
好！我照办吧
Roger. Wilco.
查尔斯
Charles.
见到你就好了
It's good to see you.
对
Yeah. Yeah.
马修，我们对婚姻有何见解？
Matt, what do we think about marriage?
糟了
Gosh.
若你是全心爱对方的话
Well, I think it's really good...
婚姻就是美好的
...if you love the person with all your heart.
一点不错
Well, exactly.
的确如此
Quite.
这些年来，参加过很多婚礼
All these weddings. All these years.
吃过那些见鬼的鲑鱼和香槟
All that blasted salmon and champagne.
来到我自己结婚的一天
Here I am on my own wedding day...
我仍然犹豫不决
...and I'm still thinking.
我可以知道你在想什么吗？
Can I ask about what?
不
No.
你最好不要知道
No, I think best not.
对不起，要耽搁一会 鲜花方面出了问题
I'm sorry, there's a delay. A problem with the flowers.
鲜花？什么？
Flowers? What?
不幸地许多宾客均患了花粉症
Unfortunately, there is a high proportion of hay fever sufferers...
他们又偏偏坐在鲜花旁边
...who've been stuck right by the damn flowers.
我们要把会众移动一下
So we're moving the congregation.
不想宣誓时喷嚏声此起彼落
Don't want the vows obliterated by sneezing.
我是否不该说 时间无多了？
Would it be out of place for me to say time's ticking by?
怎么了？告诉我
天啊
我见过嘉莉，她跟丈夫分居了
查尔斯，今天你要结婚了
应该开始了的
Should've started by now.
暂时我还能把他们骗倒
I think I've fooled them so far.
若你以笨见称的话 人们就没那么怀疑
If you have a reputation for being stupid, people are less suspicious.
你有什么意见呢？
你有三个选择，一，继续结婚
二，跟大家说 对不起，婚事告吹了
两个主意都不好，还有呢？
第三
我想不到第三个了
你好
Hello.
原来你在这里
Here you are.
准备好面对敌人了没？
Ready to face the enemy?
准备好了没？
Are we?
准备好了
Yes.
好极
Excellent.
别那么紧张！
Not so tight, Dad!
亲爱的各位
Dearly beloved...
我们在上帝和来宾的面前
...we are gathered together here in the sight of God...
聚首一堂
...and in the face of this congregation...
跟这两位共订鸳盟的男女一起
...to join together this man and this woman in holy matrimony...
这个光荣的人生阶段
...which is an honorable estate...
于混沌之初已由神所建立
...instituted of God in the time of man's innocence.
婚姻制度彰显了
Signifying unto us the mystical union...
基督与教会之间的神圣结合
...that is betwixt Christ and his church...
是不可以买卖
...and therefore is not by any to be enterprised...
也不可以鲁莽 轻率和嬉闹之心对待
...nor taken in hand unadvisedly, lightly or wantonly...
要恭敬、谨重、敬畏上帝的威严
...but reverently, discreetly, advisedly...
去面对婚姻
...soberly and in the fear of God.
所以若有人能提出…
Therefore, if any man can show any just cause...
为何他们不可结为合法夫妇
...why they may not lawfully be joined together...
请马上提出来
...let him speak now or else hereafter...
否则便永远保持缄默
...forever hold his peace.
对不起，有人有话要说吗？
I'm sorry, does someone have something to say?
你要说什么呢？
Yes? What is it?
等一下
One second.
怎么了？
我想到第三个选择了
什么？
你可以翻译出来吗？
怎么了？
What's going on?
翻译什么呢？
-他要我替他翻译 -他说什么？
- He wants me to translate. - What is he saying?
我认为新郎有疑问
他说，我认为新郎有疑问
He says, "I suspect the groom is having doubts.
我想新郎希望把婚礼延后
I suspect the groom would like to delay."
我想新郎爱着的是另有其人
这是真的吧？
我想新郎…
"I suspect the groom..."
因为这关乎你终生幸福
你必须跟你全心爱恋的人结合
还有，你的拉链没拉好
他说什么呢？
What's he saying?
他说…
He says...
他认为新郎…
...he suspects the groom...
爱上了别人
...Ioves someone else.
是真的吗？
And do you?
你真的爱着别人吗？
Do you love someone else? Do you, Charles?
是的
I do.
别拦着我！
Get out of my way!
我要干掉他！
Let me kill him!
我的天啊
Blimey.
至少我们不会忘掉这个婚礼
At least it's one we won't forget.
很多婚礼的面目都模糊了
A lot of weddings just blend into each other.
别说了
Oh, for God's sake.
这次绝对是永志难忘
This one will stick out in the memory.
真正的婚礼仪式还没开始呢
For not actually including a wedding service.
可怜的女孩
Poor girl.
我是认真的，虽然我不喜欢她
No, I mean it, poor girl! She's not my favorite person...
但是你的所作所为 实在是不可饶恕的
...but what you did today might be unforgivable.
我连想想也受不了
I can't bear to think about it.
可怜的汉
Poor Hen.
不过我们面对现实吧
Though, let's face facts.
若你在今天，即是结婚日
If you weren't sure you wanted to marry her today...
还不能确定是不是希望娶她
...of all days, i.e., your wedding day...
这一定是最正确的决定吧？
...then it must be the right decision, mustn't it?
的确不错
Quite right, Tom.
那袭礼服很漂亮 可以穿来出席派对
It was a lovely dress. Useful for parties.
他说什么呢？
What did he say, Charles?
他在自责
Says he blames himself.
不需要这样
Absolutely not.
千万不要，大卫
No, you mustn't, David.
他们都在怪责你呢
不，一人做事一人当
No, no. If there's music to be faced...
由我来面对吧
...I should be facing it.
你好
Hello.
你浑身湿透了，进来吧
Hi! You're soaking. Come in.
不，我还好
No, no. I'm fine.
已经湿透，不会更湿了
Comes a point you can't get wetter.
-好，我出来吧 -千万不要
- Okay, I'll come out. - No, please don't.
我只想来看看你可好
I just wanted to check you're okay.
有没有忙着自杀之类，但…
Not busy killing yourself or anything, but...
既然你没事，那我…
But you're fine, so...
我不该到教堂去的，对不起
I shouldn't have come to the church this morning. I'm sorry.
不！…
No! No!
这都是我的错，我才是混蛋
Wait. It was all my fault. I mean, I'm the bastard here.
我终于搞清楚，婚姻和我
And it definitely sorted out one thing, which is, marriage and me...
是无法并存的
...we're very clearly not meant for one another.
我还搞清楚另一件重要的事
Sorted out another big thing as well.
我站在教堂里
There I was, standing there in the church...
发现在这辈子中
...and for the first time in my whole life I realized I...
我首次全心全意地爱上一个人
...totally and utterly loved one person.
她并不是在我身旁穿上婚纱
And it wasn't the person standing next to me in the veil, it's...
而是现在站在我面前
...the person standing opposite me now...
站在两中的这个人
...in the rain.
还在下两吗？我察觉不到了
Is it still raining? I hadn't noticed.
事实上…
The truth of it is...
我对你一见钟情
...I've loved you from the first second I met you.
你不会再次突然离我而去吧？
You're not suddenly going away again, are you?
不，我可能会淹死，但我不走了
No. I might drown, but otherwise, no.
好的，我们进去吧
Okay, okay. We'll go in.
但首先，我要问你
But first, let me ask you one thing.
你觉得…
Do you think...
在我们干透后
...after we've dried off...
在我们相处了很久之后
...after we've spent lots more time together...
你会否同意
...you might agree...
不跟我结婚呢？
...not to marry me?
你会不会愿意
And do you think...
考虑一下，这辈子…
...not being married to me might be something you could consider...
也不跟我结婚呢？
...doing for the rest of your life?
你愿意吗？
Do you?
我愿意
I do.